Campus Construction; Collection ua950.005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Campus Construction Collection1951-1987
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany
ua950.005
1.37 cubic ft.
This collection contains planning documents used in the development and construction of the University at Albany, SUNY's Uptown campus.
Administrative History
The University's main campus, the Uptown Campus, has been described as a distinctive work of modern art. Designed in 1961-1962 by renowned American architect Edward Durell Stone (1902-1978), the campus bears Stone's signature style of bold unified design, evident in buildings from the U.S. Embassy in New Delhi to the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, D.C. Construction on the initial set of buildings began in 1962 and finished in 1971. The next building to be built on campus, Freedom Quad, opened in 1988.
The Uptown Campus is defined by a central Academic Podium complex, main fountain complex with carillon tower, and four quadrangle residence halls that dominate much of the campus.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains planning documents used in the development and construction of the University at Albany, SUNY's Uptown campus. Of particular interest are the regular progress memos providing indepth information about challenges and development with construction.
The majority of plans included in this collection (such as the 1974 plans, 30,000-40,000 student scenario) were never realized and the buildings were not constructed in the 1970s as anticipated in the previous decade.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has two series: Planning Documents and Subject Files. Both are arranged alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Architecture; Campus planning -- New York (State); College facilities -- New York (State) -- Planning; Correspondence; Clippings; State University of New York at Albany; New York State University Construction Fund
- Planning Document, 1956-1978; 1; 0.75 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains planning reports and related correspondence.
  - 1974 Comprehensive Campus Plan Updating SUNYA, 1967 August 2 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 1)
  - 1974 Comprehensive Campus Plan Updating SUNYA, 1967 June 7 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 2)
  - 1974 Comprehensive Campus Plan Updating SUNYA (1 of 2), 1968 July (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 3)
  - 1974 Comprehensive Campus Plan Updating SUNYA (2 of 2), 1968 July (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 4)
  - 1974 Comprehensive Site Plan Updating SUNYA, Summary Report, 1968 July (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 5)
  - Arena Theater, 1962-1964 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 6)
  - Building Progress Report, 1967-1971 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, Material Bound for Walter Tisdale, 1961-1966 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 10)
  - Documents, 1961-1966 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 11)
  - Documents and News Clippings, 1967-1974 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 12)
  - "Futures: State University of New York and your Children," Pamphlet, Undated (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 13)
  - Land Requirements and Building Needs of the State of New York in the Albany Area and Acquisition by the State of the Site of the Albany Country Club, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 14)
  - Lounge Space, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 15)
  - New Campus, 1962-1967 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 16)
  - New Campus, Miscellaneous, Memos, 1966-1969 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 17)
  - New Campus Rooms and Offices, Binder, Undated (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 18)
  - Planning, Buildings, 1958-1964 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 19)
  - Planning, General, 1962-1964; 1970 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 20)
  - Progress Report on SUNY 1964 Master Plan, Correspondence, 1962-1975 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 21)
  - SUNY College at Albany Site Planning Program, 1960 December 28 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 22)
  - SUNYA: Comprehensive Campus Plan Report Action Program, 1965 May 1 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 23)
  - State University of New York at Albany, Data Booklet, 1963 December 4 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 24)
  - State University of New York at Albany, Justification for Humanities Building II, Undated (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 25)
  - State University of New York at Albany, Justification for Social Science Building II, 1967 August (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 26)
  - State University of New York at Albany, Justification for Business Building II, 1967 August (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 27)
  - SUNY Planning Guidelines for Facilities at University Centers prepared by William T. Conway, Program Coordinators for University Centers, 1965 February (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 28)
  - State University of New York at Albany, Program for New Academic Building, (Annex A), 1972-1978 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 29)
  - University Building Planning, Correspondence (1 of 2), 1960-1969 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 30)
  - University Building Planning, Correspondence (2 of 2), 1960-1969 (Box 1 (1-Planning Document), Folder 31)
- Subject Files, 1951-1987; 2; 0.62 cubic ft.
  This series contains subject files including many news clippings, brochures and materials from an exhibit on campus construction.
  - Atlas Cement Promotional Brochures; SUNY Master Plan; SUNY Summary Bulletin, 1964-1965; 1970 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - Campus Environmental Improvement Program, SUNY College of Environmental Science and Forestry, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - Campus Environmental Improvement Program, SUNY College of Environmental Science and Forestry, Copy, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 34)
  - Committee of the University, 1970-1971 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 35)
  - Construction News Clippings, 1963-1967 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 36)
  - Dormitory Authority of the State of New York Annual Report, 1965-1966 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 37)
  - Edward Durell Stone, SUNYA Scrapbook (Photocopy of the original courtesy of the office of Dennis Sebeveal), 1962-1970 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 38)
  - The Environment of a College: A Study of the Campus and Construction of SUNYA, by Dennis Esposiet, 1975 October 20 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Equipment, Memos, Forms, Inventory, Proposals and Procedures, 1951; 1958-1972 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Food Services, 1962-1968 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - The Politics of Architecture: A Perspective on Nelson A. Rockefeller, Chapter 4: "The State University of New York," By Samuel E. Bleecker, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Stone and SUNYA Campus Exhibit Cards, 1987 (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Uptown Campus, 30-40,000 Student Scenario, Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Edward Durrell Stone, Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Construction, News Clippings, Photocopies, 1956-1962 (Box 3 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Construction, News Clippings, Originals, 1956-1962 (Box 3 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Construction, Highlights, News Clippings, Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Construction, News Clippings, 1963-1965 (Box 3 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Construction, News Clippings, 1966-1985 (Box 3 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)